CURRICULUM VITAE

Dr. Matilda Naawo-Poro Kamara

MB.ChB, College of Medicine and Allied Health Sciences, University of Sierra Leone.

Personal Information

Nationality: Sierra Leonean

Profession: Medical Doctor

Current location: Freetown, Sierra Leone

Contact details: kamaramatilda9198@gmail.com/+23278077306

Personal Statement

Matilda is a Sierra Leonean Medical Doctor with experience in Research and Public Health. Currently, she supervises the implementation of Carbapenem Resistance Enterobacteriaceae in West Africa and the epidemiologic Analysis of Toxoplasmosis and Co-infections in Sierra Leone. Matilda has good track record in integrated disease surveillance, advocacy, education and communication on contemporary health issues and clinical audits. She has been providing voluntary services on research since her days in Medical School. Matilda is conscientious and highly resourceful. She has good communication skills and interpersonal demeanor. Matilda's work along with other colleagues has created a solid base for stakeholder engagement on antimicrobial resistance (AMR) and other infectious diseases in Sierra Leone. To date, she has published 10 articles on topical issues in infectious disease in Sierra Leone, including studies to understand the dynamics of AMR.

Education

Institution	Location	Field of study	Degree	Start date	Completion date
College of Medicine and Allied Health Sciences	Sierra Leone	Medicine	MBChB	November 2015	August 2022

Training

Structured Operational Research and Training Initiative (SORT IT) module 1-4.

Positions and Scientific Appointments

2021 – Present Volunteering as a Research Coordinator at the Infectious Disease Research Unit, College of Medicine and Allied Health Sciences, University of Sierra Leone.

2023 – Present House Officer, Ministry of Health Sierra Leone Sciences, University of Sierra Leone

Membership and Non Scientific Appointments

- 1. Member of the Sierra Leone Medical and Dental Association
- 2. Member of Junior Doctors Association Sierra Leone

Contribution to Science

- 1. Matilda's experience in conducting research on AMR and IPC in Sierra Leone has positioned her to publish articles in this field, including:
 - a. Kamara, M.N.; Lakoh, S.; Kallon, C.; Kanu, J.S.; Kamara, R.Z.; Kamara, I.F.; Moiwo, M.M.;

- Kpagoi, S.S.T.K.; Adekanmbi, O.; Manzi, M.; et al. Hand Hygiene Practices and Promotion in Public Hospitals in Western Sierra Leone: Changes Following Operational Research in 2021. *Trop. Med. Infect. Dis.* **2023**, *8*, 486. https://doi.org/10.3390/tropicalmed8110486
- b. Lakoh S, Firima E, Williams CEE, Conteh SK, Jalloh MB, Sheku MG, Adekanmbi O, Sevalie S, Kamara SA, Kamara MAS, Barrie U, Kamara GN, Yi L, Guo X, Haffner C, Kamara MN, Jiba DF, Namanaga ES, Maruta A, Kallon C, Kanu JS, Deen GF, Samai M, Okeibunor JC, Russell JBW. An Intra-COVID-19 Assessment of Hand Hygiene Facility, Policy and Staff Compliance in Two Hospitals in Sierra Leone: Is There a Difference between Regional and Capital City Hospitals? Trop Med Infect Dis. 2021 Nov 29;6(4):204. doi: 10.3390/tropicalmed6040204. PMID: 34941660; PMCID: PMC8705290.
- c. Lakoh S, Yi L, Sevalie S, Guo X, Adekanmbi O, Smalle IO, Williams N, Barrie U, Koroma C, Zhao Y, **Kamara MN**, Cummings-John C, Jiba DF, Namanaga ES, Deen B, Zhang J, Maruta A, Kallon C, Liu P, Wurie HR, Kanu JS, Deen GF, Samai M, Sahr F, Firima E. Incidence and risk factors of surgical site infections and related antibiotic resistance in Freetown, Sierra Leone: a prospective cohort study. Antimicrob Resist Infect Control. 2022 Feb 21;11(1):39. doi: 10.1186/s13756-022-01078-y. PMID: 35189952; PMCID: PMC8862228.
- d. Lakoh S, Yi L, Russell JBW, Zhang J, Sevalie S, Zhao Y, Kanu JS, Liu P, Conteh SK, Williams CEE, Barrie U, Sheku MG, Jalloh MB, Adekanmbi O, Jiba DF, Kamara MN, Deen GF, Okeibunor JC, Yendewa GA, Guo X, Firima E. The burden of surgical site infections and related antibiotic resistance in two geographic regions of Sierra Leone: a prospective study. Ther Adv Infect Dis. 2022 Dec 7; 9:20499361221135128. doi: 10.1177/20499361221135128.
- 2. Our work over the past decade focused on generating evidence in the prevention, management and treatment of infectious diseases in Sierra Leone. Matilda has published an article on infectious diseases such as hepatitis B
 - a. Lakoh S, Firima E, Jiba DF, Kamara MN, Gashau W, Deen GF, Adekanmbi O, Yendewa GA. (2021). Prevalence of sero-markers and non-invasive assessment of liver cirrhosis in patients with Hepatitis B virus infection in Freetown, Sierra Leone: a cross-sectional study. BMC Gastroenterol. 320. PMCID: PMC8353767

Complete List of Published Work in My Bibliography: https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/?term=Kamara+MN